Dickinson, Hill and Co. Slave Trade Records MS181
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Dickinson, Hill and Co. Slave Trade Records
1850 -- 1865
1838 -- 1865
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Dickenson, Hill and Co.
MS181
0.55 Linear Feet 1 box
Arrangement
This collection is organized in one series.
Custodial History
These records were found in the Ryder Collection of Confederate Archives in 2011. The Ryder collection was cataloged as part of the WPA in 1939/1940 but in later decades the catalog ( A Calendar of the Ryder Collection of the Confederate Archives at Tufts College 1940) was forgotten and library staff added other materials to the Ryder collection, usually items from the South, from the 18th and 19th century and around the time of the Civil War.
Because the correspondence was not part of the original Ryder collection - given Ryder's congressional testimony he only picked up archival material in and immediately around the Richmond capitol and Dickenson's offices at the time were several blocks away, the correspondence was identified, removed from Ryder and a separate collection was created.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence and receipts from Dickinson, Hill and Co., a slave merchant and auctioneer firm based in Richmond, Virginia. The bulk of this collection's materials are dated from 1850 to 1865.
Related Materials
American Antiquarian Society collection
Biographical / Historical
The Dickinson, Hill & Co. slave merchant and auctioneer firm was based in Richmond Virginia and originally operated under the name R. H. Dickinson & Brother. It operated from at least 1845 until well into the Civil War. Richmond was the second largest slave market in the South, coming just after New Orleans. Dickinson & Brother and Dickinson, Hill & Company, although formally recognized as auctioneers, used traders as middle-men to buy and sell slaves in other markets and also served as financiers for traders by providing lines of credit that they could use to buy slaves.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Slavery; slave merchants; Richmond (Va.); Civil War; African American history
- Slavery transaction correspondence, 1838 -- 1865; 1850 -- 1865; MS181.001; 0.25 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains slavery transaction correspondence. Highly significant as the only extent collection of Dickenson, Hill and Co is at the American Antiquarian Society and it was assumed that Dickenson had ceased business in the 1850s.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Correspondence, 1842 -- 1845; MS181.001.001.00001 (Box Shared 14)
  - Correspondence, 1850 -- 1859; MS181.001.001.00002 (Box Shared 14)
    Includes an Annual Circular by James Turner, New Orleans, December 1st, 1857 regarding cotton, tobacco and produce trade.
  - Correspondence, 1860; MS181.001.001.00003 (Box Shared 14)
  - Correspondence, 1861; MS181.001.001.00004 (Box Shared 14)
  - Correspondence, 1862; MS181.001.001.00005 (Box Shared 14)
  - Correspondence, 1863; MS181.001.001.00006 (Box Shared 14)
  - Correspondence, 1864; MS181.001.001.00007 (Box Shared 14)
  - Correspondence, 1865; MS181.001.001.00008 (Box Shared 14)
  - Undated Correspondence, 1855 -- 1865; MS181.001.001.00009 (Box Shared 14)
  - Envelopes addressed to Dickenson, Hill & CO., 1855 -- 1865; MS181.001.001.00010 (Box Shared 14)
  - Correspondence to and from other slave merchants [?], 1838 -- 1860; MS181.001.001.00011 (Box Shared 14)
    The letters appear to be to and from a couple of other slave merchants, Mr. M. Hooker and Mrs John D. Hondren & Bros; various locations e.g. Raymond, Bovina, Columbus Georgia, Petersburg, Richmond, Vicksburg. Some correspondence relates to the death and last will of Elysbeth Cockvill, Luther M. Sanford, and Julia A. Claggett (1837 onward) by A. M. Boyd from Australia - unclear if related to slave purchase/inheritance.